<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6550.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6345 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6345.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6775 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6775.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5191 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5191.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-jadhav-roll-efficient-npdao-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="No-Path DAO modifications">No-Path DAO modifications</title>
    
    <author fullname="Rahul Arvind Jadhav" initials="R.A." role="editor" surname="Jadhav">
      <organization>Huawei Tech</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kundalahalli Village, Whitefield,</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560037</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91-080-49160700</phone>
        <email>rahul.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Rabi Narayan Sahoo" initials="R.N." surname="Sahoo">
      <organization>Huawei Tech</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kundalahalli Village, Whitefield, </street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560037</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91-080-49160700</phone>
        <email>rabinarayans@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z" surname="Cao" fullname="Zhen Cao">
      <organization>Huawei Tech</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>W Chang'an Ave</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>560037</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>zhencao.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
     in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
     necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
     purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
     specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>ROLL</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
     If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the problems associated with the use of
	  No-Path DAO messaging in RPL and a signaling improvement to improve route
	  invalidation efficiency.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t> RPL <xref target="RFC6550"/> specifies a proactive distance-vector
        based routing scheme. The specification has an optional messaging in
        the form of DAO messages using which the 6LBR can learn route towards
        any of the nodes. In storing mode, DAO messages would result in routing
        entries been created on all intermediate hops from the node's parent
        all the way towards the 6LBR.</t>

        <t>RPL also allows use of No-Path DAO (NPDAO) messaging to invalidate a
        routing path and thus releasing of any resources utilized on that path.
        A No-Path DAO is a DAO message with route lifetime of zero, signaling
        route invalidation for the given target.  This document studies the
        problems associated with the current use of No-Path DAO messaging,
        which creates route inefficiency and inconsistence.  This document also
        discusses the requirements for an optimized No-Path DAO messaging
        scheme.</t>

        <section title="Requirements Language and Terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
            NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL"
            in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
            target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

            <t>The document only caters to the RPL's storing mode of operation
            (MOP).  The non-storing mode does not require use of NPDAO for
            route invalidation since routing entries are not maintained on 6LRs
            in case of non-storing MOP.</t>

            <t>Common Ancestor node: 6LR node which is the first common node on
            the old and new path for the child node.</t>

            <t>Current parent: Parent 6LR node before switching to the new
            path.</t>

            <t>New parent: Parent 6LR node after switching to the new path.</t>

            <t>NPDAO: No-Path DAO. A DAO message which has target with lifetime
            0.</t>

            <t>Reverse NPDAO: A No-Path DAO message which traverses downstream
            in the network.</t>

            <t>Regular DAO: A DAO message with non-zero lifetime.</t>
            
            <t>This document also uses terminology described in <xref
            target="RFC6550"/> and <xref target="RFC6775"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="current_npdao" title="Current No-Path DAO messaging">
            <t>RPL introduced No-Path DAO messaging in the storing mode so that
            the node switching its current parent can inform its parents and
            ancestors to invalidate the existing route. Subsequently parents or
            ancestors would release any resources (such as the routing entry)
            it maintains on behalf of that child node. The No-Path DAO message
            always traverses the RPL tree in upward direction, originating at
            the target node itself.</t>

            <t>For the rest of this document consider the following topology:
            </t>

            <t> <figure align="center" anchor="sample_top" title="Sample
            topology"> <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
     (6LBR)
        |
        |
        |
       (A)
       / \
      /   \
     /     \
   (G)     (H)
    |       |
    |       |
    |       |
   (B)     (C)
     \      ;
      \    ;
       \  ;
        (D)
        / \
       /   \
      /     \
    (E)     (F)
        ]]></artwork> </figure> </t>
        
            <t> Node (D) is connected via preferred parent (B). (D) has an
            alternate path via (C) towards the BR. Node (A) is the common ancestor
            for (D) for paths through (B)-(G) and (C)-(H). When (D) switches from
            (B) to (C), [RFC6550] suggests sending No-Path DAO to (B) and
            regular DAO to (C).</t>
        </section>  

        <section title="Cases when No-Path DAO may be used">
            <t> There are following cases in which a node switches its parent
            and may employ No-Path DAO messaging:</t>

            <t>Case I: Current parent becomes unavailable because of transient
            or permanent link or parent node failure.</t>

            <t>Case II: The node finds a better parent node i.e. the metrics of
            another parent is better than its current parent.</t>

            <t>Case III: The node switches to a new parent whom it "thinks" has
            a better metric but does not in reality.</t>

            <t>The usual steps of operation when the node switches the parent
            is that the node sends a No-Path DAO message via its current parent
            to invalidate its current route and subsequently it tries to
            establish a new routing path by sending a new DAO via its new
            parent.  </t>       
        </section> 

        <section title="Why No-Path DAO is important?"> 
            <t>Nodes in LLNs may be resource constrained. There is limited
            memory available and routing entry records are the one of the
            primary elements occupying dynamic memory in the nodes. Route
            invalidation helps 6LR nodes to decide which entries could be
            discarded to better achieve resource utilization in case of
            contention. Thus it becomes necessary to have efficient route
            invalidation mechanism. Also note that a single parent switch may
            result in a "sub-tree" switching from one parent to another. Thus
            the route invalidation needs to be done on behalf of the sub-tree
            and not the switching node alone. In the above example, when Node
            (D) switches parent, the route invalidation needs to be done for
            (D), (E) and (F). Thus without efficient route invalidation, a 6LR
            may have to hold a lot of unwanted route entries.</t>
        </section> 
    </section>

    <section title="Problems with current No-Path DAO messaging"> 
        <t>There are following problems with the usage of current NP-DAO
        messaging</t>

        <section title="Lost NP-DAO due to link break to the previous parent">
            <t>When the node switches its parent, the NPDAO is to be sent via
            its previous parent and a regular DAO via its new parent. In cases
            where the node switches its parent because of transient or
            permanent parent link/node failure then the NPDAO message is bound
            to fail. RPL assumes communication link with the previous parent
            for No-Path DAO messaging.</t>

            <t>RPL mentions use of route lifetime to remove unwanted routes in
            case the routes could not be refreshed. But route lifetimes in case
            of LLNs could be substantially high and thus the route entries
            would be stuck for long.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Invalidate routes to dependent nodes of the switching node">
            <t>No-path DAO is sent by the node who has switched the parent but
            it does not work for the dependent child nodes below it. The
            specification does not specify how route invalidation will work for
            sub-childs, resulting in stale routing entries on behalf of the
            sub-childs on the previous route. The only way for 6LR to
            invalidate the route entries for dependent nodes would be to use
            route lifetime expiry which could be substantially high for LLNs.
            In the example topology, when Node (D) switches its parent, Node
            (D) generates an NPDAO on its behalf. Post switching, Node (D)
            transmits a DIO with incremented DTSN so that child nodes, node (E)
            and (F), generate DAOs to trigger route update on the new path for
            themselves. There is no NPDAO generated by these child nodes
            through the previous path resulting in stale entries on nodes (B)
            and (G) for nodes (E) and (F).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Route downtime caused by asynchronous operation of NPDAO and DAO">
            <t> A switching node may generate both an NPDAO and DAO via two
            different paths at almost the same time. There is a possibility
            that an NPDAO generated may invalidate the previous route and the
            regular DAO sent via the new path gets lost on the way. This may
            result in route downtime thus impacting downward traffic for the
            switching node. In the example topology, consider Node (D) switches
            from parent (B) to (C) because the metrics of the path via (C) are
            better. Note that the previous path via (B) may still be available
            (albeit at relatively bad metrics). An NPDAO sent from previous
            route may invalidate the existing route whereas there is no way to
            determine whether the new DAO has successfully updated the route
            entries on the new path.</t>            

            <t>An implementation technique to avoid this problem is to further
            delay the route invalidation by a fixed time interval after
            receiving an NPDAO, considering the time taken for the new path to
            be established. Coming up with such a time interval is tricky since
            the new route may also not be available and it may subsequently
            require more parent switches to establish a new path.</t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements for the No-Path DAO Optimization">
        <t>We identify the following requirements for the NP-DAO
        optimization.</t>

        <section title="Req#1: Tolerant to the link failures to the previous parents">
            <t>When the switching node send the NP-DAO message to the previous
            parent, it is normal that the link to the previous parent is prone
            to failure.  Therefore, it is required that the NP-DAO message MUST
            be tolerant to the link failure during the switching.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Req#2: Dependent nodes route invalidation on parent switching">
            <t>While switching the parent node and sending NP-DAO message, it
            is required that the routing entries to the dependent nodes of the
            switching node will be updated accordingly on the previous parents
            and other relevant upstream nodes.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Req#3: No impact on traffic while NP-DAO operation in progress">
            <t>While sending the NP-DAO and DAO messages, it is possible that
            the NP-DAO successfully invalidates the previous path, while the
            newly sent DAO gets lost (new path not set up successfully). This
            will result into downstream unreachability to the current switching
            node. Therefore, it is desirable that the NP-DAO is synchronized
            with the DAO to avoid the risk of routing downtime.</t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Existing Solution">
        <section title="NP-DAO can be generated by the parent node who detects link failure to the child">
            <t>RPL states mechanisms which could be utilized to clear DAO
            states in a sub-DODAG. [RFC6550] Section 11.2.2.3 states "With DAO
            inconsistency loop recovery, a packet can be used to recursively
            explore and clean up the obsolete DAO states along a
            sub-DODAG".</t>

            <t>Thus in the sample topology in Figure 1, when Node (B) detects
            link failure to (D), (B) has an option of generating an NP-DAO on
            behalf of Node (D) and its sub-childs, (E) and (F).</t>

            <t>This section explains why generation of an NP-DAO in such cases
            may not function as desired. Primarily the DAO state information in
            the form of Path Sequence plays a major role here. Every target is
            associated with a Path Sequence number which relates to the latest
            state of the target. <xref target="RFC6550"/> Section 7.1 explains
            the semantics of Path Sequence number. The target node increments
            the Path Sequence number every time it generates a new DAO. The
            router nodes en-route utilize this Path Sequence number to decide
            the freshness of target information. If a non-target node has to
            generate an NP-DAO then it could use following two possibilities
            with Path Sequence number: </t>

            <t>Let the Path Sequence number of old regular DAO that flowed
            through (B) be x. The subsequent regular DAO generated by Node (D)
            will have sequence number x+1.</t>

            <t>i. Node (B) uses the previous Path Sequence number from the
            regular DAO i.e. NP-DAO(pathseq=x)</t>

            <t>ii. Node (B) increments the Path Sequence number i.e.
            NP-DAO(pathseq=x+1)</t>

            <t>In case i, the NP-DAO(pathseq=x) will be dropped by all the
            intermediate nodes since the semantics of Path Sequence number
            dictates that any DAO with an older Path Sequence number be
            dropped.</t>

            <t>In case ii, there is a risk that the NP-DAO(pathseq=x+1)
            traverses up the DODAG and invalidates all the routes till the root
            and then the regular DAO(pathseq=x+1) from the target traverses
            upwards. In this case the regular DAO(pathseq=x+1) will be dropped
            from common ancestor node to the root. This will result in route
            downtime.</t>

            <t>Another problem with this scheme is its dependence on the
            upstream neighbor to detect that the downstream neighbor is
            unavailable. There are two possibilities by which such a detection
            might be put to work:</t>

            <t>i. There is P2P traffic from the previous sub-DODAG to any of
            nodes in the sub-tree which has switched the path. In the above
            example, lets consider that Node (G) has P2P traffic for either of
            nodes (D), (E), or (F). In this case, Node (B) will detect
            forwarding error while forwarding the packets from Node (B) to (D).
            But dependence on P2P traffic may not be an optimal way to solve
            this problem considering the reactive approach of the scheme. The
            P2P traffic pattern might be sparse and thus such a detection might
            kick-in too late.</t>

            <t>ii. The other case is where Node (B) explicitly employs some
            mechanism to probe directly attached downstream child nodes. Such
            kind of schemes are seldom used.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="NP-DAO can be generated once the link is restored to
        the previous parent">
            <t>This scheme solves a specific scenario of transient links. The
            child node can detect that the connection to previous parent is
            restored and then transmit an NP-DAO to the previous parent to
            invalidate the route. This scheme is stateful, thus requires more
            memory and solves a specific scenario.</t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Proposed changes to NPDAO signaling">
        <section title="Change in NPDAO semantics">
            <t>As described in <xref target="current_npdao"/>, currently the
            NPDAO originates at the node switching the parent and traverses
            upstream towards the root. The draft proposes to change the way
            NPDAO originates and traverses the network. The new NPDAO proposed
            does not originate at the node but instead originates at a common
            ancestor node between the new and old path. The trigger for the
            common ancestor node to generate this NPDAO is the change in the
            next hop for the node on reception of a regular DAO for the
            target.</t>

            <t>In the <xref target="sample_top"/>, when node D decides to
            switch the path from B to C, it sends a regular DAO to node C with
            reachability information containing target as address of D and
            a incremented path sequence number. Node C will update the
            routing table based on the reachability information in DAO and
            in turn generate another DAO with the same reachability
            information and forward it to H. Node H also follows the same
            procedure as Node C and forwards it to node A. When node A
            receives the regular DAO, it finds that it already has a
            routing table entry on behalf of the target address of node D.
            It finds however that the next hop information for reaching
            node D has changed i.e. the node D has decided to change the
            paths. In this case, Node A which is the common ancestor node
            for node D along the two paths (previous and new), may generate
            an NPDAO which traverses downwards in the network. The
            document in the subsequent section will explain the message
            format changes to handle this downward flow of NPDAO.  </t>

			<t>Note that even with the changed semantics, the current NPDAO
			mechanism still can be used, if the node desires to do so.</t>

        </section>
        <section title="DAO message format changes">
            <t>Every RPL message is divided into base message fields and
            additional Options. The base fields apply to the message as a whole
            and options are appended to add message/use-case specific
            attributes. As an example, a DAO message may be attributed by one
            or more "RPL Target" options which specifies the reachability
            information for the given targets. Similarly, a Transit Information
            option may be associated with a set of RPL Target options.</t>

			<t>The draft proposes a change in DAO message to contain
			"Invalidate previous route" (I) bit. This I-bit which is carried in
			regular DAO message, signals the common ancestor node to generate a
			downstream NPDAO on behalf of the target node. The I-bit is carried
			in the transit container option which augments the reachability
			information for a given set of RPL Target(s).</t>

			<t> <figure align="center" anchor="transit_info_with_i"
			title="Updated Transit Information Option (New I flag added)">
			<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type = 0x06 | Option Length |E|I|  Flags    | Path Control  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Path Sequence | Path Lifetime |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                                                               |
+                                                               +
|                                                               |
+                        Parent Address*                        +
|                                                               |
+                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+			
			]]></artwork> </figure> </t>

			<t>I (Invalidate previous route) bit: 1 bit flag. The 'I' flag is
			set by the target node to indicate that it wishes to invalidate the
			previous route by a common ancestor node between the two paths.</t>

			<t>The NPDAO thus generated by the common ancestor node needs to
			traverse downstream. An additional flag called as "Reverse NPDAO"
			(R) is added in the base DAO object to signal this change.</t>

			<t> <figure align="center" anchor="dao_obj_with_r"
			title="Updated DAO base object (New R flag added)">
			<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| RPLInstanceID |K|D|R| Flags   |   Reserved    | DAOSequence   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
+                                                               +
|                                                               |
+                            DODAGID*                           +
|                                                               |
+                                                               +
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Option(s)...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
			]]></artwork> </figure> </t>

			<t>R (Reverse DAO) bit: 1 bit flag. The 'R' flag is used to signal
			that the DAO traverses downwards.</t>
			<section title="Path Sequence number in the reverse NPDAO">
				<t>Every DAO message may contain a Path Sequence in the transit information option to identify the freshness of the DAO message. The Path Sequence in the downward NPDAO generated by common ancestor should use the same Path Sequence number present in the regular DAO message.</t>
			</section>
        </section>
        <section title="Example messaging">
			<t>In <xref target="sample_top"/>, node (D) switches its parent
			from (B) to (C). The sequence of actions is as follows:
			<list style="numbers">
				<t>(D) switches its parent from (B) to (C)</t>
				<t>(D) sends a regular DAO(tgt=D,pathseq=x+1,I_flag=1) in the
				updated path to (C)</t>
				<t>(C) checks for routing entry on behalf of (D), since it
				cannot find an entry on behalf of (D) it creates a new routing
				entry and forwards the reachability information of the target D
				to (H) in a DAO.</t>
				<t>Similar to (C), (H) checks for routing entry on behalf of
				(D), cannot find an entry and hence creates a new routing entry
				and forwards the reachability information of the target D to
				(H) in a DAO.</t>
				<t>(A) receives the DAO, and checks for routing entry on behalf
				of (D). It finds a routing entry but checks that the next hop
				for target D is now changed. (A) checks the I_flag and
				generates downstream NPDAO(tgt=D,pathseq=x+1,R_flag=1) to
				previous next hop for target D which is (G). Subsequently,
				(A) forwards the reachability information of target D
				upstream DAO(tgt=D,pathseq=x+1,I_flag=x) (the I_flag
				carries no significance henceforth).</t>
				<t>(G) receives the downstream NPDAO and invalidates routing
				entry of target (D) and then checks the reverse (R) flag and
				forwards the (un)reachability information downstream to
				(B).</t>
				<t>Similarly, (B) processes the downstream NPDAO by
				invalidating the routing entry of target (D) and then checks
				the reverse (R) flag and forwards the (un)reachability
				information downstream to (D).</t>
				<t>(D) ignores the downstream NPDAO since the target is
				itself.</t>
			</list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Dependent Nodes invalidation">
			<t>Dependent Nodes route invalidation can be handled in the same
			way as the switching node. Note that there is no way that dependent
			nodes can set the I_flag in the DAO message since they are unaware
			that their parent node is switching paths. There are two ways to
			handle dependent node route invalidation:</t>
			<t><list style="numbers">
				<t>One way to resolve is that the common ancestor does not
				depend upon the I_flag to generate the reverse NPDAO. The only
				factor it makes the decision will be based on next_hop change
				for an existing target to generate the NPDAO. Thus when the
				switching nodes and all the below dependent nodes advertise
				a regular DAO, the common ancestor node will detect a
				change in next hop and generate NPDAO for the same target
				as in the regular DAO.</t>

				<t>Another way is that the nodes always set the I_flag whenever
				they send regular DAO. Thus common ancestor will first check
				whether I_flag is set and then check whether the next_hop has
				changed and subsequently trigger NPDAO if required.</t>
			</list></t>
			<t>This document recommends the approach in point 2. The advantage
			with I_flag is that the generation of downstream NPDAO becomes more
			deterministic and the target node is still in control of its own
			routing state.</t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.
        See <xref target="RFC3552">RFC 3552</xref> for a guide.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
        &RFC2119;

        <reference anchor="CONTIKI" target="http://www.contiki-os.org">
            <front>
                <title>Contiki: The Open Source OS for IoT</title>
                <author>
                    <organization>Thingsquare</organization>
                </author>
                <date year="2012"/>
            </front>
        </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->
      &RFC3552;
      &RFC6550;
      &RFC6775;
      &RFC5191;
      &RFC6345;
    </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>

</back>
</rfc>
